Jason M Larkin

42 Lintel Dr, McMurray PA 15317 • (412) 398-8813 • jasonlarkin84@gmail.com • http://jasonlarkin.github.io

CAREER OVERVIEW AND OBJECTIVE

I have extensive experience performing experimental and numerical studies in condensed matter physics with an emphasis on nanoscale transport, fluid dynamics, and nonlinear analysis. My interests include complex systems modeling, multi-language development for applications in high-performance parallel computing, and open-source collaboration to improve the way research is performed and results are disseminated.

EDUCATION

Carnegie Mellon University Pittsburgh, PA • PhD Mechanical Engineering, 2013 GPA: 3.85/4.00

Thesis: Thermal Modeling of Disordered Materials. Numerically investigated thermal properties of crystal alloys, glasses, and organic materials using classical and *ab initio*-based atomistic techniques.

Coursework: molecular/electron structure · nanoscale transport phenomena · numerical methods

University of Pittsburgh Pittsburgh, PA • MS Mechanical Engineering, 2009 GPA: 3.70/4.00

Thesis: Statistics of Particle Concentrations in Free-Surface Turbulence. Performed experiments using novel 2D and 3D flow configurations to study turbulence as a nonlinear dynamical system.

Coursework: quantum and statistical physics · turbulence · chaos and nonlinear phenomena

University of Pittsburgh Pittsburgh, PA • BS Mechanical Engineering, 2007 GPA: 3.20/4.00

Research: Used FEM to design a model arterial bifurcation for *in vivo* study.

Steel Center AVTS Jefferson Hills, PA • CADD Certification, 2002 GPA: 3.80/4.00

Coursework: Trained in CAD using Autodesk's AutoCAD (15.6) and Inventor (5.3) to produce machined products by CAM and human machining.

EXPERIENCE

SpiralGen, Inc. (2013-2014) Software Engineer

Spiral: tool to create automatically optimized/platform-tuned digital signal processing and numerical kernels.

- Used integration work for DARPA projects (HACMS, PERFECT) to help create commercial version of the Spiral tool.
 - Designed and maintained Jenkins CI environment for build/testing.
 - Helped develop NSIS installer for Spiral tool and integration with Jenkins Cl.
 - Contributed static and context-sensitive help to Spiral's Eclipse plug-in.
 - Created native (C/C++/Fortran) and interpreted (Cython and Mex) example implementations of Spiral-generated code.
 - Helped develop HCOL implementations of robot control kernels (PID, Euler) for HACMS project.
- HACMS: DARPA project to create technology for the construction of high-assurance cyber-physical systems.
 - Integrated and tested Spiral-generated, high-assurance code with simulated Webots and physical Black-i Landshark robots using ROS.
 - Developed integrated Pentagon demo for HACMS using ROS, Webots, and TkInter.
 - Developed an automated and virtualized ROS test system for the Spiral-generated robot controller kernels.
 - Collaborated with a large/diverse team of labs (HRL, SRI) and universities (CMU, MIT, Princeton, UIUC, UPenn).
- PERFECT: DARPA project to seek revolutionary approaches and to research and develop the technologies and techniques to provide the power efficiency required to enable embedded computing systems.
 - Helped develop an installable version of the Spiral tool with an Eclipse plug-in to generate platform-optimized FFTs.

Carnegie Mellon University (2010-2012) Teaching Assistant-Heat Transfer

• Topics in conduction, convection, and radiation. Supervised recitations and substituted for lectures.

University of Pittsburgh (2008) Teaching Assistant-Advanced Fluid Mechanics

Topics in viscous flow, boundary layer theory, and scale similarity.

University of Pittsburgh (2007-2009) Lecturer-Physics

• Lectured to students and faculty on mathematics, bio-physics, turbulence, statistical and nonlinear phenomena.

Precision Therapeutics (2006-2007) Intern-Technology Development

- Worked with team of software developers and laboratory equipment specialists.
- Used CAD to fabricate components of optical microscopes and laboratory automation controls.

SKILLS

- Computing Languages: Matlab, Python, C/C++, Fortran, Java, Language development (Cython, Mex).
- Software Development: SCM (svn, git, Jenkins), make/cmake, Visual Studio/MSBuild, Eclipse, NSIS.
- Compilers/Compilation: GNU, Intel C/C++, Visual Studio, MinGW, Cython, Mex, Ant.
- High-Performance Computing: Linux/Unix cluster administration/computing, parallel computation (MPI, OpenMP), SSE/AVX vectorization.
- Cloud Computing: Amazon Web Services, Virtualization (VirtualBox, VMWare).
- General Computing: Linux/Unix OS (Ubuntu, Red Hat, CentOS, Mac), Windows OS, Microsoft Office, Libre/Open Office, GIMP.

- Open-Source Development: Github, GULP, LAMMPS, ROS, arXiv.
- Modeling: atomistic simulation, quantum chemistry, nanoscale transport, statistical and nonlinear analysis, computational fluid dynamics.
- Hardware: optics/lasers, DI/DO AI/AO interfaces, simple automation, machining, circuitry, simple robotics control.

PROJECTS

- Quantum Mechanics-Driven Prediction of Nanostructure Thermal Conductivity: served as investigator under the AFOSR with collaborators at Carnegie Mellon and University of Pittsburgh, performing calculations on the DOD's HPCMP.
- disorder: a comprehensive repository of open-source code and data from my PhD thesis, hosted on Github.
- ntpy: created this open-source collaborative effort between members of NTPL and University of Toronto.
- GULP: international collaboration with Julian Gale at the Nanochemistry Research Institute at Curtin University.
- Statistics of Free-Surface Turbulence: international collaboration with Alain Pumir at ENS Lyon, France.

PUBLICATIONS (SELECTED, 11 TOTAL)

- "Origin of the Exceptionally Low Thermal Conductivity of Fullerene Derivative PCBM Films", (in progress).
- "Decorrelating a Compressible Turbulent Flow: an Experiment", Physical Review E 82, 016301 (2010).

PRESENTATIONS (SELECTED, 15 TOTAL)

- "Evaluation of the Virtual Crystal Approximation for Predicting Thermal Conductivity", J.M. Larkin (speaker), A.J.H. McGaughey, 2013 MRS Spring Meeting San Francisco, CA.
- "The Generalized Fractal Dimensions of a 2-D Compressible Turbulence", J. Larkin (speaker), M. Bandi, W. Goldburg, 2008 American Physical Society March Meeting New Orleans, LA.

HONORS

- 2012 ASME MHNMT International Summer Heat Transfer Conference Top 5 Technical Paper
- 2011 Bennett Conference Best Presentation
- 2011 ICES Northrop-Gruman Fellow
- 2007-2009 NSF Graduate Student Research Grant University of Pittsburgh Department of Physics.

MEMBERSHIPS

 American Physical Society · American Society of Mechanical Engineers · Materials Research Society · Society of Industrial and Applied Mathematics · DOD High Performance Computing Modernization Program